<rss xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Earthquakes News -- ScienceDaily</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/news/earth_climate/earthquakes/
</link>
<description>
Earthquake News. Early detection, historic earthquakes, earthquake measurement, smart building methods and more in our earthquake research news.
</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 08:46:22 EST</pubDate>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 08:46:22 EST</lastBuildDate>
<ttl>60</ttl>
<image>
<title>Earthquakes News -- ScienceDaily</title>
<url>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/images/scidaily-logo-rss.png
</url>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/news/earth_climate/earthquakes/
</link>
<description>For more science news, visit ScienceDaily.</description>
</image>
<atom:link xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="self" href="https://rss.sciencedaily.com/earth_climate/earthquakes.xml" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<item>
<title>
'Tiny earthquakes' help scientists predict mountain rock falls
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161219134436.htm
</link>
<description>
Scientists have developed a new way to predict when mountain rock falls will happen -- in regions where people go skiing and climbing. The technique involves detecting tiny earthquakes which cause cracks in the mountain rock.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 13:44:36 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161219134436.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Above and beyond megathrusts: Draining pore-fluids dampens tremors
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161219085710.htm
</link>
<description>
While metamorphic reactions in the subducting slab liberate large amounts of fluids, low-frequency earthquakes (LFE) largely occur beneath impermeable unmetamorphosed overlying plate, and are rare beneath metamorphosed plate. Scientists suggest that undrained conditions are a key factor in the generation of LFEs, whereas well-drained conditions reduce pore-fluid pressures at the megathrust and inhibit LFEs and associated tremors.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/12/161219085710.jpg" height="117" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 08:57:10 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161219085710.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Underwater volcano's eruption captured in exquisite detail by seafloor observatory
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161215143532.htm
</link>
<description>
Seismic data from the 2015 eruption of Axial Volcano, an underwater volcano about 300 miles off the Oregon coast, has provided the clearest look at the inner workings of a volcano where two ocean plates are moving apart.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/12/161215143532.jpg" height="200" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 14:35:32 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161215143532.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Tsunami risk for Florida and Cuba modeled</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161215085924.htm
</link>
<description>
While the Caribbean is not thought to be at risk for tsunamis, a new study indicates that large submarine landslides on the slopes of the Great Bahama Bank have generated tsunamis in the past and could potentially again in the future.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/12/161215085924.jpg" height="225" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 08:59:24 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161215085924.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Tectonic shift? Study of olivine provides new data for measuring Earth's surface
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161215085909.htm
</link>
<description>
A recent study provides a new data set that scientists can use to better understand plate tectonics -- the movement of the earth's outer layer. Specifically, it contributes to understanding how plates are defined and measured, which is critical for developing computer models and predicting earthquake and volcano activity.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/12/161215085909.jpg" height="169" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 08:59:09 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161215085909.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Quake-detection app captured nearly 400 temblors worldwide
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161214090308.htm
</link>
<description>
A crowdsourced earthquake network using Android phones and the MyShake app has since February 2016 detected nearly 400 temblors worldwide, with one of the most active areas of the world the oil-drilling areas of Oklahoma. The app, downloaded almost 220,000 times, has sent back seismic waveform data that allows quite accurate assessment of magnitude and location, suitable for early warming: one of the main goals of the project.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/12/161214090308.jpg" height="208" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 09:03:08 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161214090308.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Mapping New Zealand landslides with satellites, drones, helicopters, hiking boots
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161213112341.htm
</link>
<description>
Geologists and engineers are mapping surface ruptures and some of the tens of thousands of landslides triggered by last month's magnitude-7.8 earthquake in New Zealand.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 11:23:41 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161213112341.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Earthquake faults are smarter than we usually think
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161213074527.htm
</link>
<description>
Researchers now have an answer to a vexing age-old question: Why do earthquakes sometimes come in clusters? The research team has developed a new computer model and discovered that earthquake faults are smarter -- in the sense of having better memory -- than seismologists have long assumed.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/12/161213074527.jpg" height="209" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 07:45:27 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161213074527.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
New study describes 200 million years of geological evolution
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161201092817.htm
</link>
<description>
200 million years of geological evolution of a fault in Earth’s crust has recently been dated. These new findings may be used to shed light on poorly understood pathways for methane release from the heart of our planet.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/12/161201092817.jpg" height="200" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 09:28:17 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/12/161201092817.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Groundwater helium level could signal potential risk of earthquake
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161129152509.htm
</link>
<description>
A relationship between helium levels in groundwater and the amount of stress exerted on inner rock layers of the earth, found at locations near the epicenter of the 2016 Kumamoto earthquake, has now been revealed by researchers. The scientists hope the finding will lead to the development of a monitoring system that catches stress changes that could foreshadow a big earthquake.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/11/161129152509.jpg" height="242" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 15:25:09 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161129152509.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>What's up with Madagascar?</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161128151243.htm
</link>
<description>
The island of Madagascar off the coast of Africa was largely unexplored seismically until recently. The first broadband seismic images of the island help solve a longstanding mystery: why are there volcanoes far from any tectonic boundary?
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/11/161128151243.jpg" height="147" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 15:12:43 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161128151243.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Biggest exposed fault on Earth discovered</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161128132928.htm
</link>
<description>
Geologists have for the first time seen and documented the Banda Detachment fault in eastern Indonesia and have worked out how it formed.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/11/161128132928.jpg" height="167" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 13:29:28 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161128132928.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Fault curvature may control where big earthquakes occur
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161124151450.htm
</link>
<description>
The geometry of large faults has been the focus of recent research, which has found that the big earthquakes occur where faults are mostly flat.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/11/161124151450.jpg" height="182" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 15:14:50 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161124151450.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Subduction zone geometry: Mega-earthquake risk indicator
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161124150207.htm
</link>
<description>
Mega-earthquakes (with a magnitude greater than 8.5) mainly occur on subduction faults where one tectonic plate passes under another. But the probability of such earthquakes does not appear to be even across these zones. In a new study, researchers show that mega-earthquakes mostly occur on the flattest subduction zones. Thus, the Philippines, Salomon Islands and Vanuatu areas would not be favorable to mega-earthquakes, unlike South America, Indonesia and Japan. The discovery of this new indicator should improve earthquake monitoring and seismic and tsunami risk prevention.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 15:02:07 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161124150207.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Scientists reconstruct formation of the southern Appalachians
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161121161559.htm
</link>
<description>
Around 300 million years ago, the landmass that is now North America collided with Gondwana, a supercontinent comprised of present-day Africa and South America. That clash of continents lifted tons of rock high above the surrounding terrain to form the southern end of the Appalachian Mountains now seen in Alabama, Tennessee and Georgia. A team of geophysicists has reconstructed the terminal phase of that collision and developed a new picture of how it unfolded.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/11/161121161559.jpg" height="436" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2016 16:15:59 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161121161559.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Rip in crust drives undersea volcanism</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161114143656.htm
</link>
<description>
Scientists analyzing a volcanic eruption at a mid-ocean ridge under the Pacific have come up with a somewhat contrarian explanation for what initiated it. Many scientists say undersea volcanism is triggered mainly by upwelling magma that reaches a critical pressure and forces its way up. The new study says the dominant force, at least in this case, was the seafloor itself -- basically that it ripped itself open, allowing the lava to spill out. The eruption took place on the East Pacific Rise, some 700 miles off Mexico.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/11/161114143656.jpg" height="199" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2016 14:36:56 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161114143656.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Geologists discover how a tectonic plate sank</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161114124949.htm
</link>
<description>
New information about conditions that can cause Earth's tectonic plates to sink into the earth has been released in a new report.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/11/161114124949.jpg" height="152" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2016 12:49:49 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161114124949.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Safest locations for wastewater injection</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161111133314.htm
</link>
<description>
New maps of the geologic forces contributing to earthquakes in Texas and Oklahoma could help reduce the likelihood of humanmade temblors associated with wastewater injection, say investigators.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/11/161111133314.jpg" height="259" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 13:33:14 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161111133314.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Key indicator of carbon sources in Earth's mantle</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161109132623.htm
</link>
<description>
Researchers have found evidence of varying ratios of boron isotopes in igneous rocks, known as carbonatites, of different ages.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 13:26:23 EST</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161109132623.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Some Los Angeles earthquakes possibly triggered by oil production in early 20th century
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161101100233.htm
</link>
<description>
Historical sleuthing has turned up evidence for a possible link between oil production and a handful of damaging earthquakes that took place in the Los Angeles Basin during its oil boom in the early 20th century.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/11/161101100233.jpg" height="339" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 10:02:33 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161101100233.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Entire Himalayan arc can produce large earthquakes</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161026104844.htm
</link>
<description>
The main fault at the foot of the Himalayan mountains can likely generate destructive, major earthquakes along its entire 2,400-kilometer (1,500-mile) length, a new study finds. Combining historical documents with new geologic data, the study shows the previously unstudied portion of the fault in the country Bhutan is capable of producing a large earthquake and did so in 1714.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/10/161026104844.jpg" height="199" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 10:48:44 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161026104844.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mt. Aso could erupt much sooner, scientists warn</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161020144211.htm
</link>
<description>
Damage from the 2016 Kumamoto earthquake could hasten Mt. Aso's eruption, volcanologists warn. In a new paper, scientists report new faults in the vicinity of Mt. Aso's magma chamber and volcanic cones, which they say could alter spatial and mechanical properties of Aso volcano.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/10/161020144211.jpg" height="224" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 14:42:11 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161020144211.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Earthquake series cause uplift variations at continental margins
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161017083935.htm
</link>
<description>
A new mechanism may explain how great earthquakes with magnitudes larger than M7 are linked to coastal uplift in many regions worldwide. This has important implications for the seismic hazard and the tsunami risk along the shores of many countries. The idea is that series of severe earthquakes within a geologically short period of time cause the rising of the land where one tectonic plate slips beneath another slab of the Earth's crust in a process called subduction.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/10/161017083935.jpg" height="155" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 08:39:35 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161017083935.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Geologist explores minerals below Earth's surface</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161013151146.htm
</link>
<description>
A geology researcher is going deep below Earth's surface to understand how some of the most abundant minerals that comprise Earth's crust change under pressure.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/10/161013151146.jpg" height="204" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 15:11:46 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161013151146.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Exhaling Earth: Scientists closer to forecasting volcanic eruptions
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161006101026.htm
</link>
<description>
On average, 40 volcanoes on land erupt into the atmosphere each month, while scores of others on the seafloor erupt into the ocean. A new time-lapse animation uniting volcanoes, earthquakes, and gaseous emissions reveals unforgettably the large, rigid plates that make the outermost shell of Earth and suggests the immense heat and energy beneath them seeking to escape.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/10/161006101026.jpg" height="225" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 10:10:26 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161006101026.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Earthquake risk: New fault discovered in earthquake-prone Southern California region
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161004135207.htm
</link>
<description>
A swarm of nearly 200 small earthquakes that shook Southern California residents in the Salton Sea area last week raised concerns they might trigger a larger earthquake on the southern San Andreas Fault. At the same time, scientists published their recent discovery of a potentially significant fault that lies along the eastern edge of the Salton Sea.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/10/161004135207.jpg" height="225" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 13:52:07 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161004135207.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Strength of Earth's outer shell can be measured, weak spots pinpointed
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161003111456.htm
</link>
<description>
An advanced imaging technique used to map Earth's outer shell also can provide a measure of strength, finding weak spots and magma upwellings that could point to volcanic or earthquake activity, according to a new study.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/10/161003111456.jpg" height="250" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 11:14:56 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/10/161003111456.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
New technique for finding weakness in Earth's crust
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160929142759.htm
</link>
<description>
Scientists have developed a method to estimate weakness in the Earth’s outer layers which will help explain and predict volcanic activity and earthquakes.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/09/160929142759.jpg" height="255" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 14:27:59 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160929142759.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Dense arrays of seismometers are letting scientists get a clearer look at a giant scar that underlies the American Midwest
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160928094313.htm
</link>
<description>
Deep beneath the fertile flat farmland, there is a huge scar in the Earth called the Midcontinent Rift. This ancient and hidden feature bears silent witness to a time when the core of what would become North America nearly ripped apart.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/09/160928094313.jpg" height="200" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 09:43:13 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160928094313.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
High-tech future early warning system for hurricanes, tornados and volcanic eruptions
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160927111442.htm
</link>
<description>
The Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO) has been able to detect a gravity wave wafting through space from two colliding black holes billions of years ago. Now a group has built a much smaller ring laser interferometer to explore how it could detect geophysical effects such as earthquake-generated ground rotation and infrasound from convective storms and have demonstrated the technology's potential as an early-warning system for natural disasters.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/09/160927111442.jpg" height="300" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 11:14:42 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160927111442.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Resonance in Rainbow Bridge</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160922161242.htm
</link>
<description>
Utah's iconic Rainbow Bridge hums with natural and human-made vibrations, according to a new study. The study characterizes the different ways the bridge vibrates and what frequencies and energy sources cause the rock structure to resonate. The vibrations are small, according to a geology and geophysics professor, but the study provides a baseline measure of the bridge's structural integrity and shows how human activities can rattle solid rock.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/09/160922161242.jpg" height="200" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 16:12:42 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160922161242.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Research finds way to make fracking safer</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160922150659.htm
</link>
<description>
Injecting wastewater deep underground as a byproduct of oil and gas extraction techniques that include fracking causes human-made earthquakes, new research has found. The study, which also showed that the risk can be mitigated, has the potential to transform oil and gas industry practices.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/09/160922150659.jpg" height="200" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 15:06:59 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160922150659.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Taking a fault's temperature</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160915085546.htm
</link>
<description>
Ever think about taking a fault's temperature? What would you learn? A unique experiment where temperature was continuously measured for nearly a year inside the fault that made the catastrophic 2011 magnitude 9.0 Japan Earthquake reveals the thermal signature of pulses of water squirting out of fractures in response to other earthquakes on neighboring faults.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 08:55:46 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160915085546.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Stalagmites in Indiana cave may record past earthquakes
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160912132306.htm
</link>
<description>
Stalagmites rising from the floor of a cave in southern Indiana may contain traces of past earthquakes in the region, according to a new report.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/09/160912132306.jpg" height="225" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2016 13:23:06 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160912132306.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Earthquakes can trigger near-instantaneous aftershocks on different faults
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160908151116.htm
</link>
<description>
A large earthquake on one fault can trigger large aftershocks on separate faults within just a few minutes. These findings have important implications for earthquake hazard prone regions like California where ruptures on complex fault systems may cascade and lead to mega-earthquakes.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/09/160908151116.jpg" height="170" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 15:11:16 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/09/160908151116.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
X-raying the Earth with waves from stormy weather 'bombs'
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160825151609.htm
</link>
<description>
Using a detection network based in Japan, scientists have uncovered a rare type of deep-earth tremor that they attribute to a distant North Atlantic storm called a 'weather bomb.' The discovery marks the first time scientists have observed this particular tremor, known as an S wave microseism.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/08/160825151609.jpg" height="208" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2016 15:16:09 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160825151609.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Seismic shield: Large-scale metamaterials combat earthquakes in 3-D model
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160824212210.htm
</link>
<description>
Numerical analysis considers both surface and guided waves, accounts for soil dissipation, and provides design guidelines for implementing earthquake protection using an array of ground-based cavities.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 21:22:10 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160824212210.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Post-disaster optimization technique capable of analyzing entire cities
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160824140051.htm
</link>
<description>
Scientists have created a novel method that represents a major improvement in existing post-disaster optimization methodologies. Their technique, Algorithm with Multiple-Input Genetic Operators (AMIGO) is designed to consider very complex objectives while keeping computational costs down. In addition to being the first model to factor in so many elements, AMIGO is unique for its versatility.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 14:00:51 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160824140051.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
New insights into the relationship between erosion and tectonics in the Himalayas
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160823083555.htm
</link>
<description>
Earth's climate interacts with so called surface processes -- such as landslides or river erosion -- and tectonics to shape the landscape that we see. In some regions, the sheer force of these processes has led scientists to believe that they may even influence the development of tectonics. Scientists have now disproved this assumption.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/08/160823083555.jpg" height="195" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 08:35:55 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160823083555.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Better understanding seismic hazards</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160822174104.htm
</link>
<description>
The April 2015 Gorkha earthquake in Nepal killed more than 8,000 people and injured more than 21,000. With a magnitude of 7.8, it was the worst natural disaster to strike Nepal since the 1934 Nepal-Bihar earthquake. Researchers have now discovered complex relationship between major earthquake faulting and mountain building in the Himalayas.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/08/160822174104.jpg" height="229" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 17:41:04 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160822174104.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Some signs of induced seismicity spotted in Salton Trough's geothermal production fields
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160822140520.htm
</link>
<description>
In some parts of Southern California's Brawley Seismic Zone, geothermal energy production may be increasing the background seismicity rate, but changes in earthquake rates elsewhere in the area seem to have natural causes, according to a new report.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 14:05:20 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160822140520.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
2014 Napa earthquake continued to creep, weeks after main shock
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160819120424.htm
</link>
<description>
On August 24, 2014, just south of Napa, California, a fault in Earth suddenly slipped, violently shifting and splitting huge blocks of solid rock, 6 miles below the surface. The underground upheaval generated severe shaking at the surface, lasting 10 to 20 seconds. When the shaking subsided, the magnitude 6.0 earthquake left in its wake crumpled building facades, ruptured water mains, and fractured roadways. Scientists now report that this earthquake continued to creep, weeks after the main shock.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/08/160819120424.jpg" height="200" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2016 12:04:24 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160819120424.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>The math of earthquakes</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160818090604.htm
</link>
<description>
A computational science doctoral student has successfully tied a new mathematical modeling process to the study of earthquakes.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2016 09:06:04 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160818090604.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
International ocean drilling expedition to understand causes of the Indian Ocean 2004 earthquake and tsunami
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160808091256.htm
</link>
<description>
The devastating earthquake that struck North Sumatra and the Andaman and Nicobar Islands on Boxing Day in 2004 caused a tsunami that inundated coastal communities around the Indian Ocean, killing over 250,000 people in 14 countries. That earthquake was caused by a slip on a subduction zone plate boundary fault beneath the eastern Indian Ocean, say scientists.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/08/160808091256.jpg" height="200" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 09:12:56 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160808091256.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Subduction zone earthquakes off Oregon, Washington more frequent than previous estimates
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160805230109.htm
</link>
<description>
A new analysis suggests that massive earthquakes on northern sections of the Cascadia Subduction Zone, affecting areas of the Pacific Northwest that are more heavily populated, are somewhat more frequent than has been believed in the past. The chance of one occurring within the next 50 years is also slightly higher than previously estimated.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/08/160805230109.jpg" height="246" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2016 23:01:09 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160805230109.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>The search for the earthquake nucleus</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160801113957.htm
</link>
<description>
Where a tectonic plate dives under another, in the so-called subduction zones at ocean margins, many strong earthquakes occur. Especially the earthquakes at shallow depths often cause tsunamis. How exactly are such earthquakes initiated? Which rock composition favours a break in the earth's interior that can lead to such natural disasters? A recent study points to earthquake nucleation in calcareous sediments.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/08/160801113957.jpg" height="221" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 11:39:57 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/08/160801113957.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Earth's mantle appears to have a driving role in plate tectonics
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160728143525.htm
</link>
<description>
Deep down below us is a tug of war moving at less than the speed of growing fingernails. Keeping your balance is not a concern, but how the movement happens has been debated among geologists. New clues found off Washington coast challenge a long-held notion of what moves what deep under the sea.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/07/160728143525.jpg" height="237" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2016 14:35:25 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160728143525.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Earthquake-resilient pipeline could shake up future for aging infrastructure on west coast
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160726131806.htm
</link>
<description>
A new earthquake-resilient pipeline has been designed to better protect southern California’s water utility network from natural disasters. The test mimicked a fault rupture that can occur during an earthquake when global plates begin to slip past each other, causing the ground to shift and deform.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/07/160726131806.jpg" height="200" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 13:18:06 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160726131806.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Ancient temples in the Himalaya reveal signs of past earthquakes
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160726131638.htm
</link>
<description>
Tilted pillars, cracked steps, and sliding stone canopies in a number of 7th-century A.D. temples in northwest India are among the telltale signs that seismologists are using to reconstruct the extent of some of the region's larger historic earthquakes.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/07/160726131638.jpg" height="225" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 13:16:38 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160726131638.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Magma build-up may put Salvadoran capital at risk</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160725090232.htm
</link>
<description>
The build-up of magma six kilometres below El Salvador’s Ilopango caldera means the capital city of San Salvador may be at risk from future eruptions, researchers have found.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 09:02:32 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160725090232.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Tide-triggered tremors give clues for earthquake prediction
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160721144128.htm
</link>
<description>
The triggering of small, deep earthquakes along California's San Andreas Fault reveals depth-dependent frictional behavior that may provide insight into patterns signaling when a major quake could be on the horizon, according to a new article.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/07/160721144128.jpg" height="191" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 14:41:28 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160721144128.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Elderly Japanese most resilient in wake of triple disaster, study finds
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160719110218.htm
</link>
<description>
Older people in Japan are more resistant to the impacts of disasters on their health than younger generations, a study suggests.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 11:02:18 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160719110218.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Better understanding post-earthquake fault movement
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160718142204.htm
</link>
<description>
Preparation and good timing enabled researchers to collect a unique data set following the 2014 South Napa earthquake that showed different parts of the fault, sometimes only a few kilometers apart, moved at different speeds and at different times.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/07/160718142204.jpg" height="129" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 14:22:04 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160718142204.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Record-breaking volcanic kettle on Iceland explored
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160714151425.htm
</link>
<description>
The Bárdarbunga eruption on Iceland has broken many records. The event in 2014 was the strongest in Europe since more than 240 years. The hole it left behind, the so-called caldera, is the biggest caldera formation ever observed.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/07/160714151425.jpg" height="205" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 15:14:25 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160714151425.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Earthquake prediction: An innovative technique for monitoring submarine faults
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160713115102.htm
</link>
<description>
To monitor a segment of the North Anatolian seismic fault near Istanbul, an international team of researchers has installed a network of transponders on the floor of the Sea of Marmara. The aim is to measure motion of the sea floor on either side of this segment. The data collected during the first six months reveals that the fault is probably locked in the region of this segment, suggesting that there is a progressive build-up of energy that could be released suddenly. This could cause a major earthquake in the Istanbul area.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/07/160713115102.jpg" height="133" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 11:51:02 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160713115102.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>A giant quake may lurk under Bangladesh and beyond</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160711151313.htm
</link>
<description>
A huge earthquake may be building beneath Bangladesh, the most densely populated nation on earth. Scientists say they have new evidence of increasing strain there, where two tectonic plates underlie the world's largest river delta. They estimate that at least 140 million people in the region could be affected if the boundary ruptures.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/07/160711151313.jpg" height="372" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 15:13:13 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160711151313.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Understanding tsunamis with EM fields</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160707100807.htm
</link>
<description>
New research shows that important focal parameters of tsunamigenic earthquakes -- particularly fault dip direction -- can be extracted from tsunami-borne electromagnetic fields. Such details may contribute to tsunami early warning systems that are more informative for residents of coastal areas.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 10:08:07 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160707100807.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
New study upends a theory of how Earth's mantle flows
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160706174225.htm
</link>
<description>
A new study carried out on the floor of Pacific Ocean provides the most detailed view yet of how the earth's mantle flows beneath the ocean's tectonic plates. The findings appear to upend a common belief that the strongest deformation in the mantle is controlled by large-scale movement of the plates. Instead, the highest resolution imaging yet reveals smaller-scale processes at work that have more powerful effects.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 17:42:25 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160706174225.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Penguin colonies at risk from erupting volcano</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160706114615.htm
</link>
<description>
A volcano erupting on a small island in the Sub Antarctic is depositing ash over one of the world's largest penguin colonies. Zavodovski Island is a small island in the South Sandwich archipelago and its volcano Mt Curry has been erupting since March 2016. The island is home to over one million chinstrap penguins -- the largest colony for this species in the world.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<media:thumbnail url="https://images.sciencedaily.com/2016/07/160706114615.jpg" height="457" width="300"/>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 11:46:15 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/07/160706114615.htm
</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Fukushima and the oceans: What do we know, five years on?
</title>
<link>
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/06/160630214454.htm
</link>
<description>
A major international review of the state of the oceans five years after the Fukushima disaster shows that radiation levels are decreasing rapidly except in the harbor area close to the nuclear plant itself where ongoing releases remain a concern.
<!--  more  -->
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 21:44:54 EDT</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">
https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/06/160630214454.htm
</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>